Finding Aid for Charles J. Orlebeke papers, 1962-1973
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Charles J. Orlebeke papers 1962-1973
Orlebeke, Charles J.
7 linear feet
07136 Aa 2
Executive Assistant to Governor George Romney, later Deputy Undersecretary to Romney, then secretary of the Department of Housing and Urban Development, collection includes chronological correspondence files, campaign related files, topical files. HUD files, including chronological files and topical files relating to housing and urban policy.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was donated by Charles J. Orlebeke (donor no. 9914 ) and came to the library in June 2007.
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Charles J. Orlebeke began working for George Romney in the 1962 gubernatorial campaign. He worked as an administrative assistant for Romney until becoming Executive Assistant for Research and Program Development in January of 1967. While working with Romney in the governor's office, Orlebeke focused on education, mental health, civil rights, and corrections. Orlebeke continued working with Romney at HUD as Deputy Undersecretary. Orlebeke worked at HUD from 1969-1973.
Orlebeke was born in Grand Rapids in 1934, graduating from Grand Rapids Christian High School in 1952. He earned his bachelor's degree in English and Political Science from Calvin College in 1957. He then received a Master's degree at Michigan State University in political science in 1960. In 1960-61 Orlebeke was a Fulbright scholar in Australia, and he earned his Ph.D from Michigan State University in 1965. His dissertation analyzed the Liberal Party in New South Wales, Australia.
Following his service to Romney, Orlebeke taught urban planning and public policy at the University of Illinois at Chicago. His books include Federal Aid to Chicago and New Life at Ground Zero: New York, Home Ownership and the Future of American Cities.
The Orlebeke papers dating from 1962 to 1973 are divided into two series, Governor's Office and HUD Files. The files demonstrate the close relationship between Orlebeke and George Romney. The files also shed light on housing policy trends, civil rights issues, and Michigan politics. The papers reveal a great deal about Orlebeke's public service career before he began work as a professor at the University of Illinois Chicago.
Subjects:
Elections--Michigan--1962.; Elections--Michigan--1966.; Housing policy--United States.; Michigan--Politics and government--1951-; Orlebeke, Charles J.; Romney, George W., 1907-1995.; United States. Dept. of Housing and Urban Development.; Michigan--Politics and government--1961-1970.
- Governor's Office Files
  Governor's Office files are divided into three sub-series: Chronological files, Campaign files, and Topical files. Chronological Files consist of outgoing correspondence from Romney's office. Some are signed by Orlebeke and others by Romney. The letters, mostly written to constituents, are arranged in chronological order and date from 1964 to 1969. The Campaign Files consist primarily of memos and reports regarding Romney's campaigns for governor in the 1960s. The files include information on polls, campaign strategies, and Romney's past record on issues central to the campaign. The Topical Files include memos, speeches, and other documents relating to topics such as civil rights, education, and crime. Significant portions of the material discuss the Kerner Commission, Detroit civil rights, and state police hiring procedures. There is a small amount of personal correspondence written by Orlebeke, primarily dealing with political issues or personnel issues.
  - Chronological Files
    - September 1964-December 1966, 28 folders (Box 1)
    - January 1967-January 1969, 25 folders (Box 2)
    - August 1968 (Box 2)
    - September 1968 (Box 2)
    - October 1968 (Box 2)
    - November 1968 (Box 2)
    - December 1968 (Box 2)
    - January 1969 (Box 2)
  - Campaign Files
    - Campaign Polling Strategy 1962 (Box 2)
    - Election Poll, Post-1962 Campaign 1962 (Box 2)
    - Poll March 1963 (Box 2)
    - Handwritten Re-election statement 1964 (Box 2)
    - Economic Growth 1964 (Box 2)
    - County Issues 1966 (Box 2)
    - General Campaign 1966 (Box 2)
    - Public Opinion Data 1966 (Box 2)
    - Budget 1966 (Box 2)
    - Polling Analysis, Early 1966 (Box 2)
    - Telethons 1966 (Box 2)
    - Long-Range Plans 1966 (Box 2)
    - Legislative Candidate School 1966 (Box 2)
    - Civil Rights 1966 (Box 2)
    - Mental Health 1966 (Box 2)
    - Education 1966 (Box 3)
    - Republican Party Platform 1968 (Box 3)
  - Topical Files
    - Civil Rights
      - Detroit Riot/Kerner Commission 1967 (Box 3)
      - Kerner Commission Romney Testimony 1967 (Box 3)
      - General 1967 (Box 3)
      - State Police 1968 (Box 3)
      - State Police Emergency Procedures 1968 (Box 3)
      - Speeches, with Orlebeke notes/edits 1963-1966 (Box 3)
      - Michigan Negro Ministers 1967 (Box 3)
    - Crime 1967 (Box 3)
    - Education
      - Elementary and Secondary 1967 (Box 3)
      - Memos 1965-1967 (Box 3)
      - Higher Education 1967 (Box 3)
      - Quie Amendment 1967 (Box 3)
      - Speeches and drafts 1965-1967 (Box 3)
    - Memos and other miscellaneous
      - Memos to Governor and Mrs. Little 1965-1968 (Box 3)
      - Staff Memos 1965-1968, 2 folders (Box 3)
      - Personal Correspondence 1963-1967, 2 folders (Box 3)
      - Ted Blizzard Correspondence 1967 (Box 3)
      - Gerald Ford Correspondence 1968 (Box 3)
      - Robert Griffin Correspondence 1968 (Box 3)
      - Robert Kimmich correspondence 1964 (Box 3)
    - Republican Governor's Association 1967-1968 (Box 3)
    - Social Welfare/Anti Poverty 1967 (Box 3)
- HUD Files
  HUD Files are divided into two sub-series: Chronological files and Topical Files. The Chronological Files consist of outgoing correspondence primarily written by Orlebeke. Many are written to constituents or other people who wrote to Romney, but others discuss internal HUD issues. The Topical Files range from housing policy, conferences attended, and speeches. Many files relate to Open Communities, New Communities, Operation Breakthrough, and Model Cities initiatives. Other topics addressed include environmental issues, inter-departmental cooperation, and the transition from Romney to James T. Lynn as secretary in February of 1973.
  - Chronological Files
    - January 1969-December 1972, 39 folders (Box 4)
  - Topical Files
    - Alaskan Development Task Force Oil Pipeline 1969-1971 (Box 5)
    - Consumer Affairs 1970 (Box 5)
    - Correspondence 1960-1973 (Box 5)
    - Departmental Political Liaison 1969 (Box 5)
    - Domestic Council 1970 (Box 5)
    - Environment
      - Solid Waste Sub Committee 1970 (Box 5)
      - SSI initiative 1970 (Box 5)
    - Housing
      - Policy 1970 (Box 5)
      - Airlie House Conference 1970 (Box 5)
      - Tenant/Site Selection 1970 (Box 5)
      - Policy 1971 (Box 5)
      - Equal Opportunity 1971 (Box 5)
      - Abandonment 1971-1973 (Box 5)
      - Policy 1972 (Box 5)
      - Memos 1972 (Box 5)
      - Fair Share Plans 1972 (Box 5)
      - Future of HUD 1972 (Box 5)
      - Allowance Research 1972-1973 (Box 5)
      - Memos 1970-1972 (Box 5)
      - Romney White House Memos 1969-1973 (Box 5)
      - Welfeld Memos 1969-1973, 2 folders (Box 5)
      - Office of Management and Budget 1970-1973, 2 folders (Box 5)
      - Metro Strategy 1971 (Box 6)
      - Model Cities 1968-1972, 3 folders (Box 6)
      - Downs on Future of Cities 1971 (Box 6)
      - Sam Jackson, Tony Downs exchange 1970 (Box 6)
      - New Communities 1969-1970, 2 folders (Box 6)
      - Open Communities 1969-1971, 2 folders (Box 6)
    - International Affairs 1969-1972 (Box 6)
    - Michigan 1969-1972, 2 folders (Box 6)
    - Post-Election Recommendations 1972 (Box 6)
    - Post-Moratorium 1973, 4 folders (Box 6)
    - Post-HUD Transition 1972-1973 (Box 6)
    - Program Evaluation (Box 7)
      - San Francisco Office Evaluations 1971-1973 (Box 7)
      - HUD/HEW Cooperation 1971-1972 (Box 7)
      - General 1972-1973 (Box 7)
    - Revenue Sharing 1971 (Box 7)
    - Speaking Engagements 1969-1971 (Box 7)
    - Status Report 1969 (Box 7)
    - Trips
      - Governor's Conference Committee on Community Development and Urban Relations 1969 (Box 7)
      - Camp David May 1969 (Box 7)
      - Cornerstone 1970 (Box 7)
      - Prague/UN/ECE Conference May 1971 (Box 7)
      - United Nations Conference for Human Environment 1972 (Box 7)
      - United Nations Conference for Environment 1972 (Box 7)
      - U.S.S.R 1969 (Box 7)
    - Transition 1968-1969 (Box 7)
    - Urban Issues
      - Urban Outlook 1970-1973 (Box 7)
      - Urban Affairs Council 1969 (Box 7)
    - White House Committee on Structure of Federal Programs 1970 (Box 7)
Related Material
Other papers of Charles J. Orlebeke documenting his later service in the Ford administration have been deposited in the Gerald R. Ford Presidential Library, Ann Arbor, Michigan.